(Nature sounds)
(أصوات الطبيعة)
When I first began recording wild soundscapes
أول ما بدأت بتسجيل الأصوات بالبرية
45 years ago,
منذ 45 سنة،
I had no idea that ants,
لم تكن لديّ أدنى فكرة أنّ النّمل
insect larvae, sea anemones and viruses
يرقات الحشرات، شقائق البحر و الفيروسات
created a sound signature.
كان لها صوت مميّز خاص بها.
But they do.
ولكنها تفعل.
And so does every wild habitat on the planet,
والأمر كذلك في كلّ موطن بري على وجه هذا الكوكب،
like the Amazon rainforest you're hearing behind me.
مثل الغابة المطرية الأمزونيّة التي تستمعون صوتها الآن.
In fact, temperate and tropical rainforests
في الواقع، الغبات المعتدلة والغابات المطرية الاستوائية
each produce a vibrant animal orchestra,
تنتج كلا منها أوركسترا حيوانيّة نابضة بالحياة،
that instantaneous and organized expression
ذلك التّعبير اللحظي المنتظم
of insects, reptiles, amphibians, birds and mammals.
للحشرات، الزواحف، البرمائيات، الطيور و الثديات.
And every soundscape that springs from a wild habitat
و كلّ مشهد صوتيّ منها صادر من موطن طبيعيّ
generates its own unique signature,
يشكل بصمته الخاصة،
one that contains incredible amounts of information,
التي تحتوي على كمية غير معقولة من المعلومات،
and it's some of that information I want to share with you today.
و تلك المعلومات هي ما أرغب في مشاركته معكم اليوم.
The soundscape is made up of three basic sources.
هذا المشهد الصّوتي له ثلاثة مصادر رئيسية.
The first is the geophony,
الأول هو الصوت الأرضيّ،
or the nonbiological sounds that occur
وهي الأصوات الغير بيولوجية التي
in any given habitat,
تسمع في أيّ موطن طبيعيّ
like wind in the trees, water in a stream,
مثل هزيز الريح في الشجر، خرير المياه،
waves at the ocean shore, movement of the Earth.
صوت الامواج على الشاطئ، حركة الأرض.
The second of these is the biophony.
الثاني هو الأصوات البيولوجية،
The biophony is all of the sound
وهي كل صوت أصدره
that's generated by organisms in a given habitat
كائن حيّ في الموطن الطبيعي
at one time and in one place.
في وقت واحد و مكان واحد.
And the third is all of the sound that we humans generate
و الثالث هو كلّ الأصوات التي ننتجها نحن البشر
that's called anthrophony.
و هي تسمّى الأصوات البشرية.
Some of it is controlled, like music or theater,
يمكن التّحكم في بعضها، كالموسيقى و المسرح،
but most of it is chaotic and incoherent,
لكن معظمها تكون فوضويّة و غير متناسقة،
which some of us refer to as noise.
وهو ما نطلق عليه اسم ضجيج.
There was a time when I considered wild soundscapes
كنت في يوم ما أعتبر المشاهد الصوتية الطبيعيّة
to be a worthless artifact.
لا قيمة لها.
They were just there, but they had no significance.
أنّها موجودة، لكن ليس لها معنى.
Well, I was wrong. What I learned from these encounters
لقد كنت مخطئا. ما تعلّمته من هذه المواجهات
was that careful listening gives us incredibly valuable tools
هو أنّ الاستماع الحذر يعطينا وسيلة قيّمة
by which to evaluate the health of a habitat
لنحكم على مدى صحة موطن طبيعيّ
across the entire spectrum of life.
في جميع أشكال الحياة.
When I began recording in the late '60s,
عندما بدأت التسجيل في أواخر الستينات،
the typical methods of recording were limited
كانت وسائل التّسجيل محدودة
to the fragmented capture of individual species
بالالتقاط المتجزئ للكائنات الفردية
like birds mostly, in the beginning,
كالطيور خاصة، في البداية،
but later animals like mammals and amphibians.
ثم لاحقا حيوانات كالثديات و البرمائيات.
To me, this was a little like trying to understand
بالنّسبة لي، كان الأمر كمحاولة لفهم
the magnificence of Beethoven's Fifth Symphony
روعة سمفونية بيتهوفن الخامسة
by abstracting the sound of a single violin player
من خلال استخراج موسيقى عازف كمان واحد
out of the context of the orchestra
من سياق الأوكسترا الكاملة
and hearing just that one part.
و الاستماع إلى جزء واحد فقط.
Fortunately, more and more institutions
لحسن حظيّ، بدأت العديد من المؤسسات
are implementing the more holistic models
بتنفيذ نماذج اكثر شمولية
that I and a few of my colleagues have introduced
والتي قمت انا وبعض زملائي بتقديمها
to the field of soundscape ecology.
لمجال اصوات الطبيعه في علم البيئه
When I began recording over four decades ago,
عندما بدأت بالقيام بالتسجيل منذ اكثر من اربع عقود
I could record for 10 hours
كنت اسجل لمدة عشر ساعات
and capture one hour of usable material,
واحظى بساعه واحده صالحه للاستعمال
good enough for an album or a film soundtrack
لانتاج البوم او موسيقى تصويريه
or a museum installation.
او لافتتاح متحف
Now, because of global warming,
الان وبفضل الاحتباس الحراري
resource extraction,
واستخراج الموارد
and human noise, among many other factors,
وضوضاء الانسان ولعدة عوامل اخرى
it can take up to 1,000 hours or more
أستغرق ما يقارب ال 1000 ساعه او اكثر
to capture the same thing.
للحصول على نفس الشيء
Fully 50 percent of my archive
50% كاملة من ارشيفي
comes from habitats so radically altered
تأتي من مواطن مختلفه اختلاف جذري
that they're either altogether silent
فهي اما هادئه جدا
or can no longer be heard in any of their original form.
او لا يمكن سماع اي شكل من اشكالها الطبيعيه
The usual methods of evaluating a habitat
الطرق الاعتياديه في تقييم المواطن
have been done by visually counting the numbers of species
تكمن في الاعتماد على البصر في عد الاصناف
and the numbers of individuals within each species in a given area.
واعداد الافراد في كل صنف في منطقة معينه
However, by comparing data that ties together
غير ان مقارنه هذه البيانات التي تربط بين
both density and diversity from what we hear,
كلا من كثافة وتنوع ما نسمعه
I'm able to arrive at much more precise fitness outcomes.
استطعت ان اصل الى نتائج اكثر دقه
And I want to show you some examples
وأريد أن أعرض بعض الأمثله
that typify the possibilities unlocked
التي تصور الاحتمالات المقفله
by diving into this universe.
من خلال الغوص في هذا العالم
This is Lincoln Meadow.
هذا لينكولين ميداو
Lincoln Meadow's a three-and-a-half-hour drive
تبعد لينكولين ميداو ثلاث ساعات بالسياره
east of San Francisco in the Sierra Nevada Mountains,
من شرق سان فرانسيسكو في جبال سييرا نيفادا
at about 2,000 meters altitude,
في ارتفاع يبلغ 2000 متراً
and I've been recording there for many years.
وقمت بالتسجيل هناك لعدة سنوات
In 1988, a logging company convinced local residents
في عام 1988 اقنعت شركة قطع الاشجار السكان المحليين
that there would be absolutely no environmental impact
ان لن يكون هناك اي اثر بيئي
from a new method they were trying
حيث انهم سيقومون بتجربة طريقة جديدة
called "selective logging,"
تسمى ب "القطع الانتقائي"
taking out a tree here and there
بحيث يقطعون شجره من هنا وهناك
rather than clear-cutting a whole area.
بدلا من قطع الشجر من مساحه واحده
With permission granted to record
حظيت بإذن لتسجيل
both before and after the operation,
قبل وبعد العمليه
I set up my gear and captured a large number of dawn choruses
قمت بإعداد معداتي وسجلت عدد كبير من تغريدات العصافير مع بزوغ الفجر
to very strict protocol and calibrated recordings,
لبروتوكول صارم للغايه وتسجيلات محدده
because I wanted a really good baseline.
لانني أردت أن أبني خط أساس جيد
This is an example of a spectrogram.
هذا مثال على الطيفيه
A spectrogram is a graphic illustration of sound
الطيفيه هي رسم بياني للصوت
with time from left to right across the page --
مع الوقت من اليسار الى اليمين عبر الصفحه
15 seconds in this case is represented —
في هذا المثال نعرض15 ثانيه
and frequency from the bottom of the page to the top,
والترددات من اسفل الصفحه الى اعلاها
lowest to highest.
من الادنى الى الاعلى
And you can see that the signature of a stream
وتستطيعون رؤية شارة التيار
is represented here in the bottom third or half of the page,
معروضه هنا في الثلث الاسفل او نصف الصفحه
while birds that were once in that meadow
بينما كانت الطيور في تلك الروضه
are represented in the signature across the top.
ممثله في هذه الشاره في الاعلى
There were a lot of them.
كان هناك الكثير منهم
And here's Lincoln Meadow before selective logging.
وهنا لينكولين ميداو قبل القطع الانتقائي
(Nature sounds)
(صوت الطبيعه)
Well, a year later I returned,
حسنا، عُدت بعد عام
and using the same protocols
وباستخدام نفس الطريقة
and recording under the same conditions,
وبالتسجيل تحت الظروف ذاتها
I recorded a number of examples
سجلت بعض النماذج
of the same dawn choruses,
من نفس تغريدات الصباح
and now this is what we've got.
والان هذا ما حصلت عليه
This is after selective logging.
هذا بعد القطع الانتقائي
You can see that the stream is still represented
كما ترون فالتيار مازال موجودا
in the bottom third of the page,
في الثلث الاسفل من الصفحه
but notice what's missing in the top two thirds.
لكن لاحظوا ما المفقود في الثلثين في الاعلى
(Nature sounds)
(صوت الطبيعه)
Coming up is the sound of a woodpecker.
سوف تسمعون صوت نقار الخشب
Well, I've returned to Lincoln Meadow 15 times
حسنا، عُدت إلى لينكولين ميداو 15 مره
in the last 25 years,
خلال 25 سنه
and I can tell you that the biophony,
واستطيع القول ان صوت الحياة
the density and diversity of that biophony,
الكثافه والتنوع في هذا الصوت
has not yet returned to anything like it was
لم يعد كما كان في السابق
before the operation.
قبل العملية
But here's a picture of Lincoln Meadow taken after,
لكن هذه صورة لينكولين ميداو أُخِذت بعد
and you can see that from the perspective of the camera
وتستطيعون الملاحظه من خلال زاوية الكاميرا
or the human eye,
او بالرؤية المجرده
hardly a stick or a tree appears to be out of place,
أنه بالكاد ترون عصاة او شجره خارج مكانها
which would confirm the logging company's contention
وهذا يؤكد خلاف اعتقاد شركة التقطيع
that there's nothing of environmental impact.
بنكران التأثير البيئي
However, our ears tell us a very different story.
غير أن آذاننا تروي لنا حكاية مختلفه تماما
Young students are always asking me
دائما ما يسألني الطلاب الصغار
what these animals are saying,
ماذا تقول هذه الحيوانات؟
and really I've got no idea.
وفعلا لا توجد لدي أدنى فكره
But I can tell you that they do express themselves.
لكني استطيع القول انها تعبر عن نفسها
Whether or not we understand it is a different story.
سواء كنا نفهمها أو لا هذا لا يهم
I was walking along the shore in Alaska,
كنت أمشي على الشاطيء في الاسكا
and I came across this tide pool
ومررت ببركة ماء
filled with a colony of sea anemones,
ممتلئه ومستعمره من شقائق النعمان
these wonderful eating machines,
هذه الآلات الجميله التي تأكل
relatives of coral and jellyfish.
أقاربها من المرجان وقناديل البحر
And curious to see if any of them made any noise,
وبدافع الفضول أردت أن أرى إن كان أيا منها يصدر صوتاً
I dropped a hydrophone,
قمت برمي هاتف مائي (هايدروفون)
an underwater microphone covered in rubber,
وهو مايكروفون مضاد للماء مغطى بالمطاط
down the mouth part,
في جزء الفم
and immediately the critter began
وبدأ المخلوق على الفور
to absorb the microphone into its belly,
ببلع المايكروفون في بطنه
and the tentacles were searching out of the surface
ومخالبه كانت تبحث خارج السطح
for something of nutritional value.
عن شيء ذات قيمة غذائية
The static-like sounds that are very low,
الصوت المشوش المنخفض
that you're going to hear right now.
الذي سوف تسمعونه الآن
(Static sounds)
(صوت مشوش)
Yeah, but watch. When it didn't find anything to eat --
نعم، لكن شاهدوا. عندما لم يجد ما يأكله
(Honking sound)
(صوت تزمير)
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I think that's an expression that can be understood
اعتقد أن هذا تعبير يمكن فهمه
in any language.
في أي لغه
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
At the end of its breeding cycle,
في نهاية دورة التزاوج
the Great Basin Spadefoot toad
ضفدع القريت باسين سبيدفوت
digs itself down about a meter under
يحفر نفسه حوالي متر تحت
the hard-panned desert soil of the American West,
في تراب الوست اميريكان الصحراوي القاسي
where it can stay for many seasons
حيث تبقى لعدة فصول
until conditions are just right for it to emerge again.
حتى تكون الاوضاع سليمة لها لتخرج مره أخرى
And when there's enough moisture in the soil
وتكون هناك رطوبه كافيه في التراب
in the spring, frogs will dig themselves to the surface
في الربيع، تقوم الضفادع بحفر أنفسها على السطح
and gather around these large, vernal pools
وتتجمع حول هذه الحمامات الربيعيه الكبيره
in great numbers.
في عدد هائل منها
And they vocalize in a chorus
وتطلق أصواتاً وكأنها تغني
that's absolutely in sync with one another.
بتناغم تام مع بعضها البعض
And they do that for two reasons.
وتفعل هذا لسببين
The first is competitive, because they're looking for mates,
الأول للتنافس، لأنها تبحث عن أزواج
and the second is cooperative,
والثاني للتعاون،
because if they're all vocalizing in sync together,
لأنها عندما تغني بتناغم مع بعضها
it makes it really difficult for predators like coyotes,
تجعل الأمر صعبا على الحيوانات المفترسه مثل الذئاب
foxes and owls to single out any individual for a meal.
والثعالب والبوم بانتقاء اي فرد منها لأكلها
This is a spectrogram of what the frog chorusing looks like
وهذه طيفيه تبين شكل أصوات الضفادع عندما تغني
when it's in a very healthy pattern.
في حالتها الطبيعيه الصحيه
(Frogs croaking)
(أصوات الضفادع)
Mono Lake is just to the east of Yosemite National Park
مونو ليك تقع في يسار يوساميتي ناشيونال بارك
in California,
في كاليفورنيا
and it's a favorite habitat of these toads,
وهو موطن مفضل لدى هذه الضفادع
and it's also favored by U.S. Navy jet pilots,
وهو المفضل من قبل قائدين طائرات البحريه الامريكية
who train in their fighters flying them at speeds
الذين يتدربون في مقاتليهم حيث يقودونهم بسرعه
exceeding 1,100 kilometers an hour
تزيد عن 1100 كيلوميتراً في الساعه
and altitudes only a couple hundred meters
وعلى ارتفاع بضع مئات من الأمتار
above ground level of the Mono Basin,
عن سطح الأرض في مونو باسين
very fast, very low, and so loud
سريعه جدا، ومنخفضه جدا، وصوتها عالٍ جدا
that the anthrophony, the human noise,
حيث الانثروفوني، (صوت الانسان)،
even though it's six and a half kilometers
على الرغم من بعده بستة كيلومترات ونصف
from the frog pond you just heard a second ago,
من الضفادع بركة الضفادع التي سمعتوها قبل قليل،
it masked the sound of the chorusing toads.
طغت على صوت غناء الضفادع.
You can see in this spectrogram that all of the energy
في هذه الطيفيه تستطيعون ملاحظة أن كل هذه الطاقة
that was once in the first spectrogram is gone
التي كانت موجوده في الطيفيه الأولى قد تلاشت
from the top end of the spectrogram,
من الطرف العلوي من الطيفيه،
and that there's breaks in the chorusing at two and a half,
وأن هناك فواصل في الغناء في الثانيه 2 ونصف،
four and a half, and six and a half seconds,
واربعه ونصف، و سته ونصف.
and then the sound of the jet, the signature,
وبعدها يأتي صوت الطائره النفاثه، الشاره
is in yellow at the very bottom of the page.
لونها أصفر في أسفل الصفحه.
(Frogs croaking)
(أصوات الضفادع)
Now at the end of that flyby,
الآن في نهاية هذا التحليق،
it took the frogs fully 45 minutes
استغرقت الضفادع 45 دقيقة كامله
to regain their chorusing synchronicity,
ليستردوا تناغمهم الغنائي،
during which time, and under a full moon,
وخلال هذه الفتره، وتحت ضوء القمر،
we watched as two coyotes and a great horned owl
شاهدنا اثنين من الذئاب وبومه كبيره
came in to pick off a few of their numbers.
يقومون بصرع عدد منهم.
The good news is that, with a little bit of habitat restoration
الجانب الجيد، أنه مع القليل من استعادة المواطن
and fewer flights, the frog populations,
وبعض الصراعات القليلة، سكان الضفادع،
once diminishing during the 1980s and early '90s,
تقلصت أعدادها مابين الثمانينات والتسعينات،
have pretty much returned to normal.
استطاعت أن تعود لطبيعتها مره أخرى.
I want to end with a story told by a beaver.
أريد أن أختم بقصه قالها القندس
It's a very sad story,
وهي قصه حزينة جدا،
but it really illustrates how animals
لكنها توضح كيف أن الحيوانات
can sometimes show emotion,
تستطيع أحياناً أن تُظهر مشاعرها،
a very controversial subject among some older biologists.
وهو موضوع جدلي بين علماء الأحياء.
A colleague of mine was recording in the American Midwest
زميل لي كان يسجل في الاميريكان ميدويست
around this pond that had been formed
حول هذه البركه التي قد شُكلت
maybe 16,000 years ago at the end of the last ice age.
ربما منذ 16،000 سنه مضت في نهاية العصر الجليدي الأخير.
It was also formed in part by a beaver dam
تشكلت أيضا في جزء من قبل سد القندس
at one end that held that whole ecosystem together
في نهاية واحده مسكت النظام البيئي كله
in a very delicate balance.
في توازن دقيق جداً.
And one afternoon, while he was recording,
وفي ظهيرة يوما من الايام، وبينما كان يسجل،
there suddenly appeared from out of nowhere
ظهر بشكل مفاجيء
a couple of game wardens,
اثنين من حراس اللعبه
who for no apparent reason,
والذين بدون أي سبب واضح
walked over to the beaver dam,
مشوا على سد القندس،
dropped a stick of dynamite down it, blowing it up,
ووضعوا عصاة من الديناميت، وفجروه،
killing the female and her young babies.
وقتلوا الأنثى وأطفالها الصغار.
Horrified, my colleagues remained behind
بقي زميلي بالخلف مرتعباً
to gather his thoughts
ليجمع أفكاره
and to record whatever he could the rest of the afternoon,
وليسجل ما بوسعه أن يسجل بقية الوقت،
and that evening, he captured a remarkable event:
وبذلك المساء، سجل حدث رائع وهو:
the lone surviving male beaver swimming in slow circles
القندس الذي بقي على قيد الحياة يسبح بدائره بطيئه
crying out inconsolably for its lost mate and offspring.
يبكي بشكل فادح لخسرانه أبناءه
This is probably the saddest sound
وهذا على الأرجح أكثر الأصوات حزناً
I've ever heard coming from any organism,
سمعتها من كائن حي،
human or other.
سواءاً كان إنساناً أو غيره.
(Beaver crying)
(القندس يبكي)
Yeah. Well.
نعم، حسنا.
There are many facets to soundscapes,
هناك العديد من الجوانب لأصوات الطبيعه،
among them the ways in which animals taught us to dance and sing,
منها أننا تعلمنا من الحيوانات وسائل للرقص والغناء،
which I'll save for another time.
والتي سأبقيها لأوقات أخرى.
But you have heard how biophonies
ولكنم سمعتم كيف أن الأصوات الحيوية
help clarify our understanding of the natural world.
تساعدنا على فهم الطبيعة من حولنا.
You've heard the impact of resource extraction,
سمعتم تأثير استخراج الموارد،
human noise and habitat destruction.
وضوضاء الانسان وتدمير الأوطان.
And where environmental sciences have typically
وحيث العلوم البيئية بطبيعتها
tried to understand the world from what we see,
تحاول أن تفهم العالم من خلال ما نشاهده،
a much fuller understanding can be got from what we hear.
فإننا نستطيع فهم العالم أكثر من خلال ما نسمعه.
Biophonies and geophonies are the signature voices
الأصوات الحيوية والأصوات الجيوغرافية هي دليل أصوات
of the natural world,
العالم الطبيعي،
and as we hear them,
وبينما نحن نسمعهم،
we're endowed with a sense of place,
نُمنح إحساس المكان،
the true story of the world we live in.
القصة الحقيقية للعالم الذي نعيش فيه.
In a matter of seconds,
في خلال ثوانٍ،
a soundscape reveals much more information
أصوات الطبيعة تكشف معلومات أكثر
from many perspectives,
من عدة نواحٍ،
from quantifiable data to cultural inspiration.
من بيانات قياسية إلى ايحاءات ثقافية.
Visual capture implicitly frames
التقاط إطارات ضمنية بصرية
a limited frontal perspective of a given spatial context,
في منظور محدود من سياق مكاني محدد،
while soundscapes widen that scope
بينما أصوات الطبيعة توسع هذا النطاق
to a full 360 degrees, completely enveloping us.
إلى 360 درجة، حيث تحتوينا بالكامل.
And while a picture may be worth 1,000 words,
وبينما تعبر الصوره عن 1000 كلمة،
a soundscape is worth 1,000 pictures.
صوت الطبيعة يعبر عن 1000 صوره.
And our ears tell us
وتقول لنا آذاننا
that the whisper of every leaf and creature
أن همسة كل ورقه ومخلوق
speaks to the natural sources of our lives,
تتكلم مع مصادرنا الطبيعية،
which indeed may hold the secrets of love for all things,
والتي حقا تحمل أسرار الحب لكل شيء،
especially our own humanity,
خصوصا لإنسانيتنا،
and the last word goes to a jaguar from the Amazon.
والكلمات الأخيره لنمر الأمازون.
(Growling)
(صوت النمر)
Thank you for listening.
شكراً لحسن استماعكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)